Graham Larue



SUMMARY

I am a computational biologist/bioinformatician with experience in molecular evolution and comparative genomics, finishing a PhD in Quantitative and Systems Biology from UC Merced (anticipated summer 2022). I have more than 8 years of Python experience, and have published first-author bioinformatics research and software in prominent scientific journals including Nucleic Acids Research and Current Biology. In addition to my scientific background, I have more than ten years of experience in the service industry. Going forward, I am interested in building tools for—and addressing questions in—the areas of molecular evolution, genomics and next-generation sequencing technologies and their applications.

EDUCATION

Ph.D.* - Quantitative and Systems Biology 2016 - 2022 University of California Merced

M.S. - Cell and Molecular Biology 2013 - 2015 San Francisco State University

B.S. - Biology 2002 – 2008 University of California Santa Cruz

WORK EXPERIENCE

University of California Merced | AUG. 2016 - PRESENT Graduate student

Bioinformatics and molecular evolution doctoral research in Dr. Scott Roy's group, focused on the evolutionary dynamics of minor spliceosomal introns across diverse eukaryotic genomes. Throughout my PhD I developed software to: classify genomic sequences using machine learning techniques, identify orthologous gene clusters using graph-based algorithms, extract and catalog annotated genomic feature sequences, and download and organize thousands of genome and annotation files from online databases. Additionally, I built pipelines of existing software to update eukaryotic genome annotations using NGS data, and acted as system administrator for an academic Linux server for 7+ years.

DOE Joint Genome Institute | JUN. 2019 - SEP. 2019 Summer Graduate Intern

Big data comparative genomic analysis of intron lengths in fungi.

University of California Berkeley | JUL. 2011 – JUL. 2013 Staff Research Associate I - Depts. of Neurobiology & Electrical Engineering

Electrophysiological investigation of mammalian retinal architecture in the labs of Professor Frank Werblin (Nerobiology) and Dr. Long-Sheng Fan (EE).

Santa Cruz Biotechnology | JAN. 2009 - NOV. 2010

Research Assistant

Microarray screening and sample prep. in hybridoma monoclonal antibody production group.

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

R, Julia, Perl, SQL, C++ BASIC

Python, Bash ADVANCED

TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatics: Designed and built: novel ML-based intron sequence classification algorithm (intronIC), custom ortholog and intron homology identification pipelines, command-line JGI data retrieval utility (jgi-query). Experience with: de novo transcriptome assembly, NGS-based eukaryotic gene annotation, phylogenetic tree construction, PAML, BLAST, DIAMOND, HISAT, bowtie, StringTie, STAR, AUGUSTUS, Trinity, PASA, Kallisto, Salmon, samtools, bedtools, fastq-dump

Computing: Linux system administration, GNU coreutils, grep, sed, awk, Slurm

Data visualization: Matplotlib, Seaborn

Wet lab: ELISA, microarray, confocal and two-photon microscopy, multi-electrode array, retinal tissue culture and dissection, patchclamp, rodent husbandry and euthanasia, sterile technique.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Larue, G.E., Eliáš, M., Roy, S.W., 2021. "Expansion and transformation of the minor spliceosomal system in the slime mold Physarum polycephalum." Curr. Biol.https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.050

Moyer, D.C.*, Larue, G.E.*, Hershberger, C.E., Roy, S.W., Padgett, R.A., 2020. "Comprehensive database and evolutionary dynamics of U12-type introns." Nucleic Acids Res. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaa464. (*co-first author)

Hudson, A.J., McWatters, D.C., Bowser, B.A., Moore, A.N., Larue, G.E., Roy, S.W., Russell, A.G., 2019. "Patterns of conservation of spliceosomal intron structures and spliceosome divergence in representatives of the diplomonad and parabasalid lineages." BMC Evol. Biol. 19, 162. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12862-019-1488-y.

Slabodnick, M.M., Ruby, J.G., Reiff, S.B., Swart, E.C., Gosai, S., Prabakaran, S., Witkowska, E., Larue, G.E., Fisher, S., Freeman, R.M., Gunawardena, J., Chu, W., Stover, N.A., Gregory, B.D., Nowacki, M., Derisi, J., Roy, S.W., Marshall, W.F., Sood, P., 2017. "The Macronuclear Genome of Stentor coeruleus Reveals Tiny Introns in a Giant Cell." Curr. Biol. 27, 569-575. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2016.12.057.

PERSONAL REFERENCES

References available on request

^{*}anticipated summer 2022